<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon on I Chron. 29, 18 and now published, because of the exceeding usefulness of this subject, unto all Christians of every perswasion or denomination whatsoever ... : wherein also is shewed what it is to teach for hire, and divine for money, and that  objection is answered, which some do frame ... against that maintenance ... which true gospel ministers ought to have in these dayes under that dispensation / by Richard Stafford.</title>
            <author>Stafford, Richard, 1663-1703.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1697</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 58 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A93755</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S5132</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R42863</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">38875860</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 38875860</idno>
            <idno type="VID">152402</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A93755)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 152402)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2295:27)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon on I Chron. 29, 18 and now published, because of the exceeding usefulness of this subject, unto all Christians of every perswasion or denomination whatsoever ... : wherein also is shewed what it is to teach for hire, and divine for money, and that  objection is answered, which some do frame ... against that maintenance ... which true gospel ministers ought to have in these dayes under that dispensation / by Richard Stafford.</title>
                  <author>Stafford, Richard, 1663-1703.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 22 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed, and sold by Eben. Tracy ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1697.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Advertisement: p. [2]</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: stained, tightly bound, and with print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Chronicles, 1st, XXIX, 18 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:152402:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preached On 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 29, 18.</p>
            <p>And now Publiſhed, becauſe of the Exceeding Uſefulneſs of this Subject, unto all Chriſtians of every Perſwaſion or Denomination what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, in Order to their common Salvation.</p>
            <p>Wherein alſo is ſhewed what it is to <hi>Teach for hire, and Divine for Money;</hi> and that Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection is anſwered, which ſome do frame from hence againſt that maintenance and Liveli-hood which the true Goſpel miniſters ought to have in theſe dayes under that Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By Richard Stafford</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Beloved,</hi> when I gave all diligence to write unto you of the common Salvation, it was needfull for me to write unto you, and exhort you, that ye ſhould earneſtly contend for the Faith which was once delivered unto the Saints <hi>Jude,</hi> 3.</p>
            <p>And ſo here it is needful for me to write unto you, and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort you, that ye ſhould Pray without ceaſing in theſe, or the like words, <hi>O Lord God of Abraham, Iſaac and of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael our Fathers; keep this for ever in the Imagination of the thoughts of the heart of thy People, and prepare their hearts unto thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed, and Sold by <hi>Eben. Tracy,</hi> at the three Bibles on <hi>London Bridge.</hi> 1697.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_notice">
            <pb facs="tcp:152402:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>ADVERTISEMENT.</head>
            <p>THeſe are to give Notice, That I have ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral other Practical <hi>Sermons</hi> or <hi>Diſcourſes</hi> of mine own Compoſing lying by me in Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſcript. Which if they, who have the Plen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> or Competency of this World would thus <hi>Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crate</hi> ſome part of their <hi>Gain</hi> and <hi>Subſtance</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Lord Micah. 4, v. 13. As to be <hi>ready to diſtribute,</hi> and <hi>willing to Communicate</hi> towards the outward Labour and Charge of the Print<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Publiſhing of them, it would be for the Glory of God, <hi>(in making known his Truth.</hi> Iſa 38. 19.) And for the Edification and benefit o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> his Church and People; and conſequently i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> would be a <hi>good Work</hi> in ſuch Perſons wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſhall be helpful and any ways aſſiſtant herein for which they would be Rewarded by God in the Life that is to come.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Charge them that are Rich in this World, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> they do good, that they be rich in good works, rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to diſtribute, willing to communicate, laying up in ſtore for themſelves a good foundation againſt the time to come, that they may lay hold on Eternal Life.</hi> 1 Tim. 6. v. 17, 18, 19. <hi>This is a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful ſaying, and theſe things I will that thou affirm conſtantly, that they which have believed in God, might be careful to maintain Good Works; theſe things are good and profitable unto men.</hi> Titus.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:152402:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>1 Chron. 29, v. 18.</bibl>
               <q>O Lord God of Abraham. Iſaac, and of Iſrael our Fathers, keep this for ever in the Imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of the thoughts of the heart of thy peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and prepare their Hearts unto thee.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>HAving deeply conſidered and weighed in my Spirit, how our Condition ſtands God ward or towards God; how it is at ſome times afar off and Eſtranged from him, and again at other times it is indifferent well towards him; ſometimes we have a moſt lively and Spiritual ſence of God, and we are all for Obdience, Honour and Reverence of his Name, again at other times we are apt to deny God above, goe on Frowardly in the way of our heart, ſetting up for our ſelves, <hi>and thou haſt ſaid in thine heart, I am, and none elſe beſides <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e.</hi> Iſa. 47 v. 11. Being our own Men, and, <hi>Who is Lord over us?</hi> As the Weather is ſometimes Bright and clear, and then again dark and cloudy: Even ſo it Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens ſucceſſively and interchangeably as to the Influences and Communications between God and our Souls, and as to our ſence of him, and the things of his <hi>Kingdom.</hi> There is none ſo very Godly and Religious, yea his beſt Saints and Servants on Earth, but hath ſometimes an Eclipſe and cloud come over his inward Man, which hinders from the Shining of the Sun of Righteouſneſs. He hath ſome forſak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings; withdrawings, Departing and hidings of the Face of God from him; ſo on the other hand, There is hardly any ſo very Ungodly, Wicked or Ignorant; There is none ſo Vain and frollickſome, but in ſome little Time or Interval is now and then in a Serious Godly mood. The Truth of both which Obſervations ye may know by conferring and comparing your own Experiences with what I here declare to be mine. As alſo from hence ye may eaſily Gather and apprehend the Reaſon of my chooſing this Text. Though I will not ſo arrogantly ſay and pretend, <hi>It ſeemed good to the Holy Ghoſt and us,</hi> yet if I have the Real fear of the Lord
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:152402:3"/> in my heart, then the Promiſe is Not to me only, but to every Private and Faithful Chriſtian <hi>Him ſhall He Teach in the way that He ſhall chooſe.</hi> Pſal. 24. v. 12. So that I may be bold from hence to ſay, that I am Directed and Taught of God, as I now pray for his Aſſiſtance therein, To Treat and Handle theſe words unto ye at this Time and Opportunity, It being an help and Remedy as to both theſe failings. That is to ſay, as to the Godly, Righteous, and Wiſe, when they are for the moſt part in a Right Diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Temper of Soul towards God, but ſometimes they are given to Backſlidings <hi>Heſ.</hi> 4 2. To forget and looſe the Spiritual lively ſenſe of him, <hi>O Lord, why haſt t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ou made us to err from thy wayes? and hardened our Hearts from thy fear?</hi> Iſa. 63, 17. This laſt ought not to be at any time but when they are Zealous and Devout towards him, then there is need to Pray and Endeavour alſo, <hi>O Lord Ged of Abraham, Iſaac. and of Iſrael our Fathers, keep this fer ever in the Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gination of the thoughts of the Heart of thy People, and prepare their hearts unto thee,</hi> And ſo when the other ſort have ſome fits of Holineſs for a ſeaſon they have now and then a mind and think it would be better for them, both Living and Dying, to lead a Godly Rel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ous, Strict, Holy and Preciſe Life. <hi>Like Herod who heard <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>hn Baptiſt Gladly.</hi> and did ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things: But theſe only bring forth Fruit for a very ſhort Seaſon, or rather they do not ſo much as bring forth Fruit, but they are blaſted or blighted in the Bloſſom; for it all Evaporites into fruitleſs wiſhes and wouldings towards God, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> her then into actual Good it ſelf or, only ſome Good Thoughts and In I nations, without coming forth into Act and Performance. But if it was alwayes ſo in their Hearts, as it is now and then for a ſhort ſpace, it would at length come forth into Act and Performance. And ſince the beginning of a thing is in Thought and Intent of the Heart towards it; and the tendencies and beginnings ſhould be cheriſhed and furthered according to that <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Method,</hi> for who hath deſpiſed the day of ſmall things? And He <hi>doth not break the bruiſed Reed, nor Quench the ſmoak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Flax.</hi> If ſinners and thoſe that are yet Unconverted, are now and then rouſed and ſtirred up by a quickning and ſoul ſearching Sermon, If they are almoſt perſwaded to be a Chriſtian, and they perceive within them (it may be as
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:152402:3"/> they By chance drop in to hear the word Preached with Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority and Life,) an inclination to accept of Gods terms, to Ariſe and be Saved Yea whatever leaſt good in their Mind towards the Lord God at any time doth appear forth, Ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by Word or Act on, or ſuch like, here again, as it is ſaid, Take with you Words, and turn to the Lord, and ſay unto him <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſ.</hi> 14, 2, ſo this very ſame form of ſound Words, may be here fitly and appoſitely uſed, <hi>O Lord God of Abraham, Iſ ac, and of Iſ ael our Fathers, keep this for ever in the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magination of the thoughts of the heart of thy People, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare their hearts unto thee.</hi> So prepare their heart, that thoſe Strangers and Unconverted may at length be Actually brought over unto God.</p>
            <p>As I have acquainted ye with the Reaſon of my chooſing this Text, ſo by what hath been hitherto opened and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained concerning the drift and deſign of our intended Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe thereon, ye may know and perceive the uſefulneſs of this Subject, for in the order and courſe of my Miniſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, I would only inſiſt upon Uſeful Subjects which doe come within thoſe three Ends of Preaching, or, Propheyſing, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14 3, The Apoſtle Paul there Writes of <hi>ſpeaking unto Men to Edification, and Exhortation and Com o t;</hi> for in the ſequel and connexion of this our Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon it may appear, that if the things of God and of his Kingdom are kept for ever in the Imagination of the Thoughts of the heart of thy People, they will be Edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, yea and Exhorted, to what? Even to what is expreſſed in the following Verſe, <hi>To keep thy Commandments thy Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies and thy Statutes, and to do all theſe things,</hi> 1 Chron. 29, v. 19. Which God hath made known in his Reveal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Word; and as theſe things are alwayes kept in the heart, and done accordingly, there will be comfort to the Man, or Woman who doth ſo; which comfort if it be true, and ſound, and well grounded, as here it is, it is a precious Sign, Token, and fore runner of Eternal Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, Happineſs, and Bleſſedneſs.</p>
            <p>Theſe Words, <hi>O Lord Ged of Abraham, &amp;c.</hi> Are part of <hi>David</hi>'s Prayer and Thankſgiving, when Himſelf and the People offered willingly towards the Building of the Temple, as you may find by reading over this whole Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the 1 <hi>Chron,</hi> 29. which ſhewed forth a Good Mind, and a good Work towards God. It is ſaidinthe verſe immediately
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:152402:4"/> foregoing the Text, <hi>I know alſo my God that thou trieſt the heart, and haſt Pleaſure in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>prightneſs. As for me in the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>prightneſs of my heart,</hi> (Sirs, this is moſt excellent Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity, and carries along with it excellent matter of Inſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for ye) I have willingly offered all theſe things, and now I have ſeen with joy thy People, which are preſent here to offer willingly unto thee. This ſame Phraſe of <hi>Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering willingly,</hi> is repeated over no leſs then five or ſix times in this chapter. Whereby is ſhewn forth that exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſtreſs the Holy Ghoſt (which acquaints us with the Mind and Will of God) doth lay thereon, and how it is delighted therewith. Hereby alſo we are taught and Inſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that whatever we do in the worſhip, Service, and Work of the Lord, We ſhould be ſure to doe it all <hi>Willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</hi> In the Worſhip of God, or Hearing his Word, or wait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on him in his Ordinances; we are to perform it willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. This is contrary to thoſe in <hi>Amos, 8, v. 5. Who ſay When will the new Moon be gone, that we may ſell Corn? and the Sabbath, that we may ſet forth Wheat.</hi> And who ſaid al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, Behold, <hi>what a wearineſs is it,</hi> Mal. 1, v. 13. Unto whom the Worſhip of God is in Nature of a task, or drud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gery, and they complain of the length and tediouſneſs there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, becauſe themſelves find no delight therein, through their own Unſanctified and Unrenewed Natures. And when they come to it, it is as it were of neceſſity, for they think of God as an hard Maſter, who hath rigorouſly and peremp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torily impoſed it, and they uſe it to Preſerve their Souls) as they imagine) from Hell fire. This is the manner of the wordly Worſhippers, and of the Multitude who go to the Church, or Congregations according to cuſtom, or juſt to pacify and ſatisfie Natural Conſcience. But there is another Mind far different from this in the true Saints and ſervants of the Lord. <hi>Thy People ſhall be willing in the day of thy Power,</hi> Pſal. 110, v. 3. And ſo they are willing in the day of his Grace and forbearance: What they do in Order to God, either in acts of Worſhip or other things, They doe it not Grudgingly, or of Neceſſity, and as it were a forced buſineſs, but willingly and with all their heart. <hi>My heart is towards the Governours of Iſrael, that offered themſelves wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly among the People: Bleſs ye the Lord,</hi> Judges, 5, v. 9. The ſame Rule holds of all the Duties and things pertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:152402:4"/> to God and Religion, as of Alms-giving, <hi>Every Man ſhall Give as he is able, according to the Bleſſing of the Lord thy God which he hath given thee.</hi> Deut. 16. v. 17. Every Man according as he He purpoſeth in his heart, ſo let him give, not Grudgingly or of neceſſity; for God loveth a cheerful or willing Giver. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 9. 7. And ſo God loves a cheerful Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipper. God loves a cheerful and willing Servant. <hi>Thou ſhalt rejoyce before the Lord thy God in all that thou putteſt thine hand unto.</hi> Deut. 12. v. 18. Thou ſhalt ſerve the Lord thy God with joyfulneſs of heart, for the abundance or Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiency of things which he gives thee. So that not only the Chapter out of which we have taken the Text, but alſo the Paralel places of Scripture doe confirm the ſame Word, that People ſhould offer themſelves willingly to the Service of the Lord. Remember and carry away with you this Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verb, willingly. And ſo they ſhould come willingly to the place of Hearing his Word. I have oftentimes thought that if I had a ſettled Congregation of mine own in a great and Populous City (the Lord grant and Effect this my Deſire, notwithſtanding there are many Adverſaries) I would cauſe theſe Words to be written in Great Capital Letters at the door of the Aſſembly, <hi>He that hath Ears to hear, let him hear.</hi> Which doth alſo imply, that he that will not, may ſtay a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way. Becauſe that every thing in Order to God, or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining to Religion, ſhould be free and willing; and peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſhould perform it of their own Accord, of a Voluntary Motion of their own; for this have I learned and found from out of the Scriptures of Truth, that with ſuch kind of Sacrifice or Worſhip God is well pleaſed, and alſo he is Glorifi'd therein.</p>
            <p>The Jews did <hi>Offer willingly</hi> towards the Building of the Temple, but now we are told under the Goſpel, that the moſt High dwelleth not in Temples made with Hands, as ſaith the Prophet <hi>Heaven is my Throne, and Earth is my Footſtool.</hi> Acts. 7. v. 47. For where ever two or three are Gathered together in his Name, God is the midſt of them. and he is ſerved acceptably, equally, and all one upon the Sea-ſhore, or in an open Field, or in the Room of an Houſe as what is called Churches or Steeple-Houſes, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the contradiction of Ignorant Zealots here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in; who in this retain that relick and remainder
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:152402:5"/> of that Popiſh Maxim, Ignorance is the Mother of Devoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: for they doe not love that whom they Ignorantly Worſhip, ſhould be declared unto them; nor what they are Ignorantly zealous for, That the Truth hereof ſhould be laid open and Manifeſt unto them. For as Chriſt according to the Fleſh, was laid in the Manger of a Stable, ſo his Word is of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten more Simply and Purely Preached in places that ſeem mean to the outward Eye, then in finer Buildings. Though here to purſue the like Reaſoning with that of David, <hi>Lo I dwell in an Houſe of Ceder, but the Ark of God dwelleth with in Curtains.</hi> 2. Sam. 7. v. 2. So I can in no wiſe approve of in my Mind (I ſpeak here after my judgment, and alſo I think according to the Spirit of God) That where ſome of the Subſtantial and Rich People have dwelling Houſe and Rooms of their own, altogether or Sufficiently large for the number of People, that they ſhould ſave and prefer the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> it may be for Entertainments, and making proviſion for the fleſh) and in the mean while ſuffer the Word of the Mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> High God to be Preached in an Old and Rotten Barn. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> profeſs ſeriouſly that when I have ſeen this, it hath been matter of <hi>ſecret</hi> Indignation and vexation to me; for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> would have nothing done on this Earth, by the Inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants thereof, which ſhould in the leaſt ſavour, or make ſhew of Enmity againſt, or deſpiſing of the Great and I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible God, whoſe Word is there Preached, and whoſe Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip is there uſed. I do again ſpeak after my Judgment, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> would ſeem better if the Members of the Reſpectve Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations did offer willingly to make the place juſt decen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> without Sumptuouſneſs on the one hand, or Sordid mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs on the other.</p>
            <p>It was a good Mind and Reſolution when David ſaid unto Araunah, <hi>Nay, but I will ſurely it buy of thee at a pria neither will I offer burnt-offerings unto the Lord my God, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> that which hath coſt me nothing.</hi> 2. Sam. 24. v. 24. A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the ſame ſhould be drawn forth into Example and Imitatio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> by the other Saints and Servants of God; they ſhould in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> wiſe content themſelves to ſerve God with a Religion which hath coſt them nothing. I ſay, and I will prove it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> our of the Scriptures of Truth, that even day labourers, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Vine-dreſſers, yea the pooreſt and meaneſt of the People ſhould no wiſe content themſelves to ſerve God with a Rel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:152402:5"/> which coſt them nothing, Let him that ſtole, ſteal no more, but rather let him labour, working with <hi>his hands the thing which is good, that he may have to give to him that needeth.</hi> Eph. 4. 28. From hence it appears that thoſe in the Ordinary and moſt mean Employments, are to diſpoſe and Give in Alms what is more then ſatisfieth themſelves. Even this Command extends to thoſe who were ſo Poor, as they before were forced to ſteal to ſerve their own neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities. And ſo from the Reaſon of that General and Indefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite Command to all People, Thou ſhalt not appear Empty before the Lord thy God; and in their Offerings every one was to do according to their ſeveral Ability, They that could not goe to the Price of a Lamb, were to give a Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle or two young Pigeons, and by what is ſaid in the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel of her that caſt in two mites into the Treaſury, which makes a farthing, from the like and ſame proportion and Analogy of things, It may be ſurely gathered, That the Lord doth require and Expect that All, High and Low, Rich and Poor, who ſerve him, ſhould Miniſter ſomewhat unto him of their Subſtance, and ſhould ſerve him with that which coſts them ſomething, whither it be a farthing, Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, twelve pence or more, Each Perſon according to his Ability. Whatever is more then the neceſſity and conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency of his Family, ſhould be caſt into the Offerings of God, to be diſtributed, or expended towards the Place where his Worſhip is called on, for the maintenance of his Miniſters, for the relief of his Poor Saints and Servants; for Good works, as is the Publiſhing or Propogation of his Eternal Truth, or ſuch like. It is Obſervable that though the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> did <hi>Breach the Goſpel freely</hi> in divers places, and he ſaith himſelf, <hi>He robbed other Churches, taking wages of them to do you ſervice.</hi> 2. Cor. 11. 8. Yet he all a long ſpeaks and pleads for the lawfulneſs and juſtifiableneſs to accept of, and receive the free Offerings of Chriſtian Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, for his Preaching and Miniſtery of the Goſpel. <hi>Who goeth to Warfare any tims at his own charges? Who planteth a Vineyard and eateth not of the fruit thereof, or who feedeth a Flock and eateth not of the milk of the Flock? If we have ſown unto you Spiritual things, is it a great matter that we ſhall reap your carnal things? If others be partakers of this Power o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:152402:6"/> you, Are we not rather? Nevertheleſs we have not uſed this Power, but ſuffer all things, leſt we ſhould hinder the Goſpel of Chriſt. Do ye not know that they which Miniſter about Holy things, live of the things of the Temple, and they which wait at the Altar are partakers at the Altar, Even ſo hath the Lord Ordained that they which Preach the Goſpel ſhould live of the Goſpel. But I have uſed none of theſe things.</hi> 1. Cor. 9. 11, 12, 13, 14. By which laſt Speech, and his aforeſaying, we <hi>have not uſed this Power, but ſuffer all thinge leſt we ſhould hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Goſpel of Chriſt,</hi> is ſhewed forth his own good mind, that he ſought the furtherance of the Goſpel, and the good of ſouls more then his own private Ends or Gain. And ſo where any one will not forbear <hi>Preaching,</hi> though nothing be miniſtered to him for the ſame; and <hi>they that are taught is the Word, do not communicate unto him that teacheth, in all good things.</hi> Gal. 6. 6. Which would be according to the Apoſtolical Rule, nevertheleſs he doth not matter or regard, or at leaſt not ſo much as deſiſt, refrain, or be leſs diligent in that God Duty, whither he hath any thing for it or not, this is a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain ſign and Evidence, that ſuch a one doth not <hi>Teach <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> hire, nor Divine for Money.</hi> Micah. 3, 11. That is, he doth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> make it his Principal Ultimate or only End; for this is the thing here Reproved, it being no ſin as appears from the afore quoted place out of the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> if it be not neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily required, but only freely offered, and willingly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributed by the People.</p>
            <p>He that doth put a difference, and ſhew a difference Eze<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 22. 26. Or doth well diſtinguiſh, he doth rightly. Teach i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the nature of the things of God and pertaining to his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom. (If I were but Righteouſly or equally dealt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al by my Kindred according to the fleſh, there would be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> need for me to make publick an Intimation of this nature. But their doings towards me have confirmed the Truth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> that Old Obſervation, that if any one in a Family doe ſerv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> God more then Ordinary, he ſhall be ſure to be oppreſſed Cruſhed, kept under hatches, and be deſtitute, afflicted, and tormented by them.</p>
            <p>As to <hi>offer willingly</hi> is highly acceptable and pleaſing in the ſight of the Lord, ſo to prevent, Anticipate or be before hand, even before any one doth ask or intimate, This
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:152402:6"/> an Inſtance of <hi>Offering</hi> willingly, and it is God like, <hi>for thou preventeſt him with the Bleſſings of Goodneſs,</hi> Pſal. 21. 3 E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven before a Prayer or Deſire is Offered for and in behalf of them. <hi>And it ſhall come to paſs that before they call I will anſwer, and while they are yet ſpeaking, I will hear.</hi> Iſa. 65. 24. For as one Rightly Obſerves, It doth reſemble the Deity, and it is God like to do free, ready, and ſoon acts of Benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence. When we read ſuch places of Scripture as this fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, they doe not ſtand Recorded for nothing, but for our Admonition and Inſtruction, upon whom the Ends of the World are come. The Inhabitants of the Land of Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man brought Water to him, that was thirſty, they <hi>Prevented</hi> with their Bread him that fled <hi>Iſa.</hi> 21. 14. Mark here a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain this Word, <hi>prevented;</hi> for ſuch as was thirſty, or fled here did not ask for it, but the others did imagine and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend that the others might have need and occaſion of it, and ſo they were ready before hand to meet and ſupply them with it. Like as <hi>Melchiſedech brought forth Bread and Wine to Abraham as he was returning from the Slaughter of the Kings.</hi> And ſo on the other worſe hand, <hi>Amalek</hi> is curſed and puniſhed, becauſe he met not the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> with Bread and Water as they came through, and from out of the Wilderneſs. From what is written, <hi>Becauſe that he remembered not to ſhew Mercy</hi> Pſal. 109. 16. We learn, that where we can do any act of Good, Kindneſs or Compaſſion to one another (whither it be to Friend or E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy) and we doe it not, the Lord, when he comes to enter into judgment, and we are to receive for the deeds done in the Body, will impute that as ſin to that man or woman who refuſed, neglected, or omitted it. For though now it be reckoned as a matter indifferent, and it is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly ſaid they doe him no harm, if they doe him or her no good; yet in this caſe, The not doing of Kindneſſes when it is in our Power for to do them, is indeed doing hurt or injury; becauſe of the real harm, injury or loſs which ſuch a one Suſtains for want of having that Kindneſs done for him.</p>
            <p>As was before mentioned, <hi>My heart is towards the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours of Iſrael, that Offered themſelves willingly among the People,</hi> ſo if we may ſo ſpeak after the manner of Men,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:152402:7"/> The Heart of God is towards ſuch of his Servants and Creatures that <hi>Offer themſelves willingly</hi> to do ſuch and ſuch Things for his Glory, Worſhip, and Service, and be doing Good unto Men, or who are for what links theſe three to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, <hi>Glory to God in the Higheſt, Peace on Earth, and Good will towards Men;</hi> and each one in his Vocation and place doth Offer out himſelf willingly towards the things that make for the ſame.</p>
            <p>Here again is another Real Act and Inſtance of <hi>Offering willingly,</hi> when they can and doe bereave their own Soul of Good, to doe good for others: which again will be a doing Good to their own Soul at long run, for <hi>the Merciful Man doeth Good to his own Soul.</hi> Prov. 11. 17. I mean when People are contented to ſuffer Hunger or pinch their own Belly for once or twice to feed and ſupply that which hath more often wanted it; when for all out of their obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to the command of God they will bring that Bread and Water which they do almoſt want themſelves. Like the Widow of <hi>Zarephath,</hi> who had but an handful <hi>of Meal, and a little Oyl in a Curſe.</hi> 1. Kings, 17. 12. And yet out of that ſhe was to Suſtain and feed <hi>Elijah</hi> the Prophet of the Lord, which ſhe did, and had no lack. Sirs, here is ſome Truſt of God in theſe things. When thou haſt but a little, thou doſt Give diligence Gladly to Give freely, and <hi>Offer willingly</hi> of that little; and thou canſt not only ſay ſo in outward Words, but truſt that the Lord will provide a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle more againſt the time, and when that ſame little is gone, <hi>And they that know thy Name will put their truſt in thee: For thou, Lord, haſt not forſaken them that ſeek thee</hi> Pſal. 9. 10. <hi>O taſte and ſee that the Lord is good: Bleſſed is the Man that truſteth in him. O fear the Lord ye his Saints: for there is no want to them that fear him.</hi> 
               <q>The Young Lions do lack, and ſuffer hunger: But they that ſeek the Lord ſhall not want any good thing.</q> Pſal. 34. 8, 9, 10. And ſuch of his Saints do not fear to be Impoveriſhed or come to want through the Service of God, but they Offer <hi>willingly,</hi> and do things not <hi>Grudingly,</hi> or of Neceſſity, even in the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſive part of Religion, and they indeavour to ſave, or truſt that the Lord (who teacheth to profit) will make it up as much unto them another way.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:152402:7"/>
            <p>So far we have ſhewed of this Excellent Duty, of <hi>Offering willingly</hi> as we ſhewed the Coherence of the Text, upon the Reſidue of the Chapter, for the ſame thing of <hi>Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering willingly</hi> is intended and meant therein all one as what is ſaid in the following Words, <q>To keep the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments, the Teſtimonies and Statutes of the Lord</q> for that they ſhould <hi>Offer willingly</hi> towards the Worſhip and Service of God, is alſo One of his Commandments, and Teſtimonies and Statutes. But here it holds true as to both, People are for <hi>Offering willingly,</hi> and for keeping the Commandments, the Teſtimonies and the Statutes of the Lord ſometimes only, and not alwayes. They are for doing it now and then, but not for ever: and therefore in Oppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on unto this Corrupt Nature of theirs, whoſe goodneſs is as the Morning cloud, and as the early dew, it ſoon paſſeth away: As alſo to help and ſupply this defect and failure of theirs, <hi>David</hi> here Prays by the Spirit <q>O Lord God of <hi>Abraham, Iſaac</hi> and of <hi>Iſrael</hi> our Fathers keep this for ever in the Imagination of the thoughts of the hearts of thy People, and prepare their heart unto thee.</q> There is another Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralel and alike Scripture unto this in Deut 5. 29. <q>O that there were ſuch an heart in them, that they would fear me, and keep all my Commandments alwayes.</q> Obſerve this Adverb, alwayes; for it is the ſame in Signification with that of our Text, <q>keep this for ever in the Imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the thoughts of the heart of thy People, that it might be well with them, and with their Children for ever.</q> This is alſo brought in upon a good Mood and Temper of the People; when they were in an Obedient frame of Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit unto the Lord God. When they had ſaid unto <hi>Moſes,</hi> 
               <q>Speak thou unto us all that the <hi>Lord our God</hi> ſhall ſpeak unto thee, and we will hear it, and do it; and the <hi>Lord</hi> hereupon anſwered, They have well ſaid in all that they have ſpoken.</q> A very good Commendation of our God unto his Creatures; But the cream of the matter is; They have well ſaid, if they will hold unto it, and thereupon God himſelf Wiſhes and deſires, for it is expreſſed after the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Men, <q>O that there were ſuch a Heart in them that they would fear me and keep all my Commandments al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes.</q> By which kind of Speech and Expreſſion, he doth foreſee and miſtruſt, That that Good Reſolution of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:152402:8"/> theirs which was in them, would be Temporary, ſudden, Goe off and paſs away again, as truly ſo it did.</p>
            <p>And truly it is ſo whither we Preach or Pray never ſo much, That all good things, the Great Truths of God, all Faith and all Knowledge<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the ſence of his Name, and Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to all the Words of his Law, may be kept for ever in the Imagination of the Thoughts of our Hearts, that in the day of tryal and hour of temptation, we may have all along at the very ſame Time, a Divine Overruling Thought, which may reſiſt the Temptation, and keep and determine unto God and Duty; Yet ſtill nevertheleſs it is ſenſible and Experienced, that theſe things are not kept for ever in the Imagination of the thoughts of our hearts. I have often wiſhed and deſired for my ſelf (Pray, Let your hearts alſo go along with me herein) O that I were alwayes and for ever ſuch towards God, as I am ſometimes in my moſt Devout and Solemn Approaches unto him in Prayer, or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> his Ordinance of Hearing his Word; that I had alwayes the ſame Reverence, Godly fear, and Horrour and Dre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of the Deity, when I am walking about, or ſitting ſtill, a I have ſometimes upon my bended knees. That I had the ſome conſtant Gravity, ſeriouſneſs and trembling of Spirit in the midſt of Life, Health and Proſperity, and when thing go moſt according to wiſh, as I have upon the apprehenſion of any great danger, or under affliction, or as I ſhall have when I come to lye upon the Bed of laſt ſickneſs and dying. It is Impoſſible to recall or vain to wiſh for, as to what is paſt. But O that I might, for all the few and Evil dayes remaining of my Pilgrimage, throughout all my ſucceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Life, have that conſtant Univerſal Obedience, Honor and Preferring of God above things, as I ſhall indeed deſire that I had had when I come to think my laſt. juſt as whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> I ſhall perceive that I am yeilding up the Ghoſt, and ſurren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring up my Spirit to the God that gave it. O that my Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit may now henceforth and for ever, ſo Obey and be give up unto the Father of the Spirits of all fleſh, as ſhe will ref<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect and wiſh ſhe had done, when ſhe ſhall be Summoned to appear before him, And ſhe is to take her flight into the Inviſible World. O that I did ſo want on God all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> day. Pſal. 25. 3. And was in the <q>fear of Lord all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:152402:8"/> long, <hi>Prov,</hi> 23. 17.</q> As I have ſometimes for two or three Hours together in a Morning. As it is written in <hi>Jude, 19. Theſe be ſenſual, having not the Spirit:</hi> So I have too often obſerved and experienced, that after my too full Meals, I have been damped and for a time loſt that ſence of God and Spiritual Things, which before I had. O that I might therefore ſo Eat &amp; Drink to his Glory, that I might be near the ſame in the midſt of or immediately after receiving of my neceſſary and moderate Food as I was before. And ſo It ſhould hold in the other circumſtances and Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Life, to keep this for ever in the Imagination of the Thoughts of our heart, whither Sleeping or Waking, in labour or Idle, when we ſit in our Houſe, or when we walk and journey in the way, and when we lye down or riſe up, in a Word, whatever our hand findeth to doe, or whatever we are Imployed about; I ſay again This ſtill is to be kept for ever in the Imagination of the Thoughts of our hearts, even <hi>to keep the Commandments, the Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies and the Statutes of the Lord God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>David here rightly Prays that the Lord would keep this in the Imagination of the Thoughts of our hearts;</q> for as it is written, <hi>Except the Lord keep the City, the Watch and watcheth but in vain.</hi> Pſal. 127. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>. So except the Lord keep our heart, all our keeping of them is in vain, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding it is commanded, keep thy heart with all diligence for out of it are the Iſſues of Life. The Scripture is no where not in the leaſt inconſiſtent with it ſelf; but the Truth of the Matter ſeems to ſtand on this wiſe: we are firſt to Pray unto God Immediately to keep our hearts, and hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo done, we are to endeavour after the ſame as much as ever we can our ſelves. For we learn evidently from what is written, <hi>We then as Workers together with him, beſeech you alſo, that yo receive not the Grace of God in vain.</hi> 2. Cor. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>. 1. <hi>Work out your own Salvation with fear and trembling:</hi> 
               <q>For it is God which worketh in you both to will and to do of his Good pleaſure,</q> 
               <hi>Phil.</hi> 2. 12, 13<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Whereunto I alſo labour, ſtriving according to his Working, which worketh in me mightily. <hi>Col.</hi> 1. 29. That there is a Power and Ability implanted in, and given unto man by God the Creator to Work together with his Grace. It ſhould be a conſtant
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:152402:9"/> rule that whatſoever we are commanded or directed to pray for, or whatever we do pray for, we ſhould indeavour af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it our ſelves. <hi>Whereunto I alſo labour, ſtriving accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his working, which worketh in me mightily,</hi> Even ſo we ſhould labour and ſtrive after the ſame thing. And ſo to our preſent caſe, we ſhould pray unto God in the firſt place, to keep this ſtill in the Imagination of the thoughts of our hearts and then indeavour, labour, and ſtrive accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to whatever we can, to do ſo our ſelves.</p>
            <p>That it is the Particular Province and Prerogative of Almighty God, to keep the hearts of the children of Men, We have the Scriptures affirming in divers places, for the Lords Vineyard is the hearts of Men, <hi>For the Vineyard of the Lord of Hoſts is the Houſe of Iſrael.</hi> Iſa. 5. 7. And we Read there how he Fenced it, and Gathered out the Stems thereof, and planted it with the choiceſt Vine, and built a Tower in the midſt of it, and alſo made a Wine-press therein. <q>In that day Sing ye unto her, A Vineyard of Red Wine, I the Lord do keep it, I will water it every Moment, leſt any hurt it, I will keep it Night and Day.</q> Iſa. 27. 2, 3. Here it is affirmed and ratified twice in the ſame Verſe, that God will keep it leſt any hurt it; which nothing can do, but Satan or his Temptations, as they ſeduce to ſin or evil. Nothing but ſin can hurt the heart of Man. And if we would ſuffer that the Lord ſhould keep our hearts Night and Day, and that he Guide us continually, ſo that our ſelves here are under keepers, and ſtand upon our watch; for thus the Scripture doth direct in other places, ſo as to prevent and keep out the comings in and Acts of Sin; and then it is effectually prevented, leſt any hurt it. <hi>And all thy Children ſhall be taught of the Lord, and great ſhall be the peace of thy Children,</hi> Iſa. 54. 13. The right conſequence here is, that when they <hi>are taught of God,</hi> they ſhould learn of him; and when he doth inſtruct and would Guide them, they ſhould receive the inſtruction, and follow his Guidance. God doth Keep, Guide, and Teach the hearts of the Children of Men, in an Inviſible manner, but yet it is ſenſible to the hearts of his faithful People. <q>The Wind bloweth where it liſteth, and thou heareſt the ſound thereof, but canſt not tell whence it cometh, and whither it goeth;
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:152402:9"/> ſo is every one that is born of the Spirit, <hi>John.</hi> 3. 8.</q> So likewiſe is every one that is Taught, Guided, or Inſtructed by the Spirit. And ſo in like manner God doth keep the hearts of his People. As the Diſtillings of Dew in a clear Night are not perceived; ſo God moves himſelf as it were upon, and Communicates himſelf to the hearts of his Creatures in the ſtill voice of his Word and Spirit. <q>For God ſpeaketh once, yea twice, yet man perceiveth it not. In a dream, in a Viſion of the Night when deep ſleep falleth upon men, In ſlumberings upon the Bed. Then he openeth the Ears of Men, and ſealeth their Inſtruction</q> 
               <hi>Jel.</hi> 33<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 14, 15. 16. And ſo when we are in the moſt ſtill, retired, abſtracted and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated manner. When we becom the Man whom thou choſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt and cauſeſt to approach unto thee. <hi>Pſal,</hi> 65. 4. Then it is that God doth reveal and manifeſt himſelf unto us. When we are Obedient and Holy, Sobet and Temperate, when we are Chaſt and do not regard the deſire of women, being Purified &amp; Sanctified, theſe are furtherances &amp; forwardings, or helps towards God making known his Mind and Will un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us. As again There are Hindrances and Obſtructions. The Principal and I may almoſt ſay, the only hinderance is Sin; for it is that which makes that wide Chaſm, or Diſtance be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween God and the creatures, <hi>Your Iniquities have ſeperated between you and your God.</hi> Iſa. 59. 2. Sin or Iniquity in the General do produce this aceurſed and evil effect.</p>
            <p>But they may be clearly Specified, and reduced to theſe three ſorts, Namely, what doth defeat, and render of none, or rather of leſs effect the Seed ſown, or Choke the Word Preached, the ſame is the Principal hindrance to Gods keeping this ſtill in the Imagination of the Thoughts of the hearts of this People, <hi>The cares of this World and the deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs of Riches, and the luſts of other things entring in</hi> Mark. 4. 19. And ſo where it is written, <hi>Take heed to your ſelves, leſt at any time your hearts be over-charged with ſurfetting, and drunkenneſs, and cares of this Life, and ſo that day come upon you unawares.</hi> Luke. 21. 34. We learn and underſtand from all this put together, what the hinderances are. And when we know them what they are, we may avoid and let them alone, or at leaſt not be let or hindered by them. They are the <hi>Cares of this World, and of this Life, and the deceitful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Riches, and the luſts of other things,</hi> or Gluttony and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:152402:10"/> drunkenneſs and ſuch like. And then the heart being too much ſet upon Viſible Objects, and Viſible things, this doth draw off and alienate from, and make to forget and looſe the ſence of him that is Inviſible, as alſo of the Inviſible things of his Kingdom. As was before ſaid, We ſhould Pray un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God to keep this ſtill in the Imagination of the Thoughts of the hearts of thy People; even that purpoſe, and Reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, To keep his Commandments, his Teſtimonies and his Statutes; ſo we ſhould likewiſe Endeavour, Strive and Labour after the ſame. And as we Taſte and See, Feel and Experience, know and perceive what are the Clogs, Interruptions, and Hinderances, ſo we ſhould avoid and not give way unto them. The Temper and State of our Soul is Various and ſeveral as it ſtands towards God. <hi>For thou haſt lifted me up, and caſt me down.</hi> Pſal. 102. 10. Now and then it is Good enough, and then it is bad, dark and cloudy again, according as we commit Sin, and are plung<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into the cares of this Life, or are Intereſted and concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the luſts of other things. The Servants of God are a diſcerning and obſerving People. They look within the glaſs of the Word, and alſo they reflect and look within their own Souls, and they compare both together. And indeed eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one muſt obſerve and practice the like methods, who would make any Growth, Proficiency, Increaſe and Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement in the Chriſtian Life: Here we might well rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and do, that if we can be and are Godly at one ſeaſon, why not at another? and ſo if our Minds are now fraught with and Furniſhed, and full of Reverence and fear of the Divine Majeſty, ſo it may be likewiſe at another time, and thus we might go through the ſeveral Stages and Periods of Life even to ſerve God in Righteouſneſs and true Holineſs all the dayes thereof, and to fear continually before him: For by the like means<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which we do perform it at one time, we may Endeavour after it at another. There is an unſeen Enemy, who ſtands at our Elbow, I mean Satan and his Temptations, who prompts us to commit Sin in each Act or Inſtance of Tryal, even in our very meals, to eat to exceſs or commit Gluttony, and ſo in other things alike; and here we ſhould be upon our Watch, to Pray and lift up our hearts, Avoid or get behind me Satan, ſo that he ſhould not get ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, nor prevail over us. The Uſe and Benefit here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hereof
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:152402:10"/> will be exceeding Great; for beſides that this is th only making our Calling and Election ſure. It is the only way and means to Aſſertain Salvation unto our Selves, ſo the more Good any one doth, and the more he abſtains from Sin and from all appearance of evil, It will be proportioned accordingly unto that Man or Woman in the Future Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence, and they will receive a more full and greater Reward. This is the ſum and concluſion of the whole mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tet, and the drift and deſign of all Preaching, That People may ceaſe to do Evil, and learn to do Well, as much as ever they can. But why is it ſaid in our Text? <hi>O Lord God of Abraham, Iſaac Iacob</hi> or <hi>Iſrael.</hi> The Reaſon hereof ſeems to be near to this effect and purpoſe. We read how that <hi>Abraham, Iſaac, Jacob,</hi> or <hi>Iſrael</hi> were precious Saints and ſervants of God in their day, and in their Generation, and thereupon God came to be in Covenant with them, and was in a peculiar manner their God. <hi>Now therefore if you will Obey my Voice indeed, and keep my Covenant, then ye ſhall be a peculiar treaſure unto me above all people: For all the Earth is mine.</hi> Exod. 19, 5. And ſo God is the God of all Men and Women, as they are his Creatures, and the Inhabitants of his Earth, but by the way of Peculiarity, Emphaſis or Property or Propriety, he is only the God of his Saints and ſervants, <hi>The Lord knoweth them that are his.</hi> 1. Tim. 2. 19. But is He the God of Abraham, Iſaac, and Jacob only<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> No, for he is the God of all their Children alſo, even of all thoſe who do the Works of Abraham and of all thoſe who are faithfull as Abraham was, who is ſtiled the Father of the Faithful. But becauſe that from the Loins of theſe three Men, who did every one of them ſucceſſively fear<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and ſerve the Lord in their time; <hi>There Sprang even of one</hi> (for One was his Son, the other was his Grand-Son) and him as good as dead, ſo many as the Stars of the Skie in Multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, and as the Sand which is by the Sea-ſhore Innumera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, even a very Numerous Poſterity, and great People, who were Elect and Beloved of God before the other Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Earth, for their Fathers ſake. Therefore the Scriptures in ſundry and many places Stiles him by the God of <hi>Abraham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Jacob.</hi> But whereas it is ſaid in the cloſe of our Text, <hi>And prepare their hearts unto thee.</hi> Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by another Truth doth ſhine and appear forth, viz. That
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:152402:11"/> God hath but one way in bringing many Sons &amp; Daughters unto Glory, or in bringing all the Sons and Daughters of Men that ever go there, unto Heaven. Even by preparing their heart unto himſelf. That is, by bringing them to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in this world, that he may bring them to his own home in<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the World to come. <hi>Moreover Brethren, I would not that ye ſhould be ignorant how that all our Fathers were under the clouds and all paſſed through the Sea: And did all eat the ſame Spiritual Meat, And did all Drink the ſame Spiritual Drink:</hi> 1 Cor. 10. 1, 3, 4. And ſo all the People that ever went to Heaven<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and are now a going in their journey to it, or who ſhall be born, and Inherit that Happy Countrey hereafter, they all Go the very ſame way. If you ask me what that way is It is the old Trodden way by the Saints, <hi>And a way, and it ſhall be called the way of Holineſs.</hi> Iſa. 35. 8. It is the way of Univerſal Obedience, and confirming all the words of Gods Law to do them (and not Obſerving ſome, and Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glecting others as the manner of many is) It is the way of drawing near to God, to which the Promiſe is <hi>James.</hi> 4. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>And he will draw nigh unto you.</hi> Or as it is in the laſt words of our Text,: <hi>by preparing their heart unto him,</hi> Which again is done (as appears by the Context, and the verſe immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately following) <hi>By keeping this for ever in the Imagination of the Thoughts of our hearts,</hi> to have a determinate, Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, and Perfect heart and mind to keep conſtantly, and at all Times the Commandments, the Teſtimonies, and the Statutes of the Lord. And alſo ſuch Divine Truths, or Knowledge of the things of God and of his Kingdom, ſhould be for ever kept in the heart, with the Sence and<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of them, which ſhould Actually perſwade, exhort and incline unto the ſame good thing.</p>
            <p>From this manner of Speech, <hi>Prepare their heart unto thee</hi> and from what is elſe-where written, <hi>And he ſhall go before him in the Spirit and Power of Elias, to turn the hearts of the Fathers to the Children, and the diſobedient to the wiſdom of the juſt, to make ready a People prepared for the Lord.</hi> Luke. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 17. We ſee that there are two things which the Miniſtry and Preaching of the Word doth drive and intend at, the Firſt is To Convert Sinners, and to turn to Righteouſneſs and then the next thing is in a further Degree and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiency, even to make them a People prepared for the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:152402:11"/> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to prepare their hearts unto thee. Which two things have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the only Ends and Intent of all the Sermons that ever Preached in this Place, or deſign to Preach throughout all my Succeeding Life. Remembring ſtill, that as the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>de or Hook are in the hands of the Gardiner for digging <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the Earth, or Pruning of Trees, even ſo we Creatures <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Miniſters, are but living Inſtruments in the Hands of God, to dig or cultivate our own hearts, or the hearts of other People. <hi>For we are Labourers together with God, ye are Gods Husbandry, ye are Gods Building.</hi> 1. Cor. 3. 9. And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> as before Obſerved, How <hi>David</hi> Prayed immediately to God, <hi>To keep this for ever in the Imagination of the Thoughts of the heart of thy People,</hi> though we are to Endeavour to keep it our ſelves, ſo Here again he lifts up the other Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion unto God Immediately, prepare their hearts unto thee<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Though here again we are to Endeavour to prepare our own hearts. As alſo beſides this, there is the Word ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, and the Miniſtry or Preaching thereof (who hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth are become labourers together with God) It is a Bold and Great Expreſſion of the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> which he ſpeaks forth by the Spirit, <hi>to make them a people prepared for the Lord,</hi> or to <hi>prepare their hearts unto him.</hi> So hath God pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided and Eſtabliſhed, and ſo ſhould Things Cooperate and Work together for the common Salvation of mankind.</p>
            <p>But Beloved that are here preſent, I hope that moſt of ye are among the latter ſort; I mean that ye are a-verted from Sin, and Converted to God in the General, and ye are amongſt thoſe, who are preparing for the Lord, or prepar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their hearts to ſeek him, or preparing for Heaven. For when we Read and Conſider, how that Jeſus, our forerun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner is gone to <hi>prepare a Place for you.</hi> John. 14. 3. To this muſt anſwer, ſome act of your own, that is <hi>to prepare</hi> your hearts for that place. <hi>Whom</hi> (that is Jeſus) <hi>We preach<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> warn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing every man, and teaching every man in all Wiſdom, that we may preſent every man perfect in Chriſt Jeſus.</hi> Col. 1, 28. It is ſtrange for you to conceive hereof, but yet it is true, that God will judge that the Word Preached in this place, ſhall be a warning and Teſtimony to all the Inhabitants of this Town and Neighbour-hood, though not the twentieth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> nor yet hardly the hundredth part of them do come to hear. Remember I told you of it before. I Ground this Affirmati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:152402:12"/> from theſe Words of Paul who ſpake thus by the Spirit, and yet it is certain, that every man dwelling in the City of <hi>Coloſs,</hi> and the adjacent Villages did not hear <hi>Paul.</hi> Never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs ſeeing that every man thereabout might have heard<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> him Preach if they would, and all had a Rumour and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port thereof, though they would not hear him themſelves, therefore according to the method, Interpretation, &amp; accou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of God according to which he will judge and proceed at the laſt day; He did <hi>Warn and teach every man, that we may preſent every man perfect in Chriſt Jeſus.</hi> Whereunto I (and ſo ſhould all ye that hear me this day) alſo labour, ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving according to his Working, which worketh in m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> mightily. <hi>Col.</hi> 1. 29. And ſo ye alſo are to labour accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Working of God, which worketh in ye mightily. Do ye not Perceive at my ſpeaking this unto ye, ſome Groaning of Spirit, and Interceſſions and deſires after the ſame which cannot be uttered? That ye may be meet to be partakers of the Inheritance of the Saints in Light. We know ſenſibly what is the miſery and vexation of world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſapointments; and there is no diſapoinment like that of Heaven, which indeed is a Thing poſſible and to be feared, and the utmoſt care is to be taken againſt it all our Life long. <q>
                  <hi>Iſrael</hi> hath not obtained that which He ſeeketh for, but the Election hath obtained it, and the reſt were blinded. <hi>Rom.</hi> 11. 7. Let us therfore fear, leſt a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe being left us of entring into his Reſt, any of you ſhould ſeem to come ſhort of it</q>. <hi>Heb.</hi> 4. 1. There is no Preaching like unto that of Experimental Preaching; and pray, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>et your hearts go along with me, and confer Notes, and compare Experiences, By Examining and Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning with your own Spirits, whilſt I declare how it is with mine own Soul. As it is written, <hi>For the Lord hath called thee as a Woman forſaken and grieved in Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit.</hi> Iſa. 54. 6. This laſt Thing of grieved in Spirit, is Exactly mine own condition. I find nothing in me, but I am alſo ſhewed the Reaſon thereof. And this Grief of Spirit in me doth not ſo much ariſe from wordly or outward Things, becauſe I know the <hi>utmoſt of them,</hi> that they are but little and <hi>ſoon</hi> paſs away, and ſeem afterwards juſt all one as a dream <hi>when one awaketh.</hi> But as it is elſewhere written, <hi>I Remembred God and was troubled: I complained,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:152402:12"/> and my Spirit was overwhelmed. Selah.</hi> Pſal. 77. 3. So as I think of God and of the other World (for the Powers of the world to come do ſhake my Soul) thence does ariſe all my Trouble, Grief, and Fear. Why ſo O Man? It is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I have not that degree of Aſſurance and well Ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Hope which I would have, and do Preſs after ſtill. Pray, Think upon, and Obſerve this. It is a Secret An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh and Vexation of Spirit, that I am growing in years, and <hi>Gray hairs do here and there appear upon me;</hi> That the Morning of Youth is over and paſt, and will never return again in this State; and I haſte to that where I ſeem no more to be, and yet I have not laid in a Better and more aſſured Foundation againſt the time to come, which I would ſtill ſeek to make it yet more and more ſure. <hi>Cauſe me to know the way wherein I ſhould walk, for I lift up my Soul to thee.</hi> Pſal. 143, 8. That doubt and Jealouſy, and miſgiving of heart, Leaſt I neglect, or am afraid to do the Will of God, doth cauſe no little Vexation of Spirit in me. Cauſe me to hear thy Loving Kindneſs early in the Morning, for in thee do I truſt &amp;c. Herein I ſpeak of thoſe Extraordnary Works and Tryals, which God is ſometimes pleaſed to call ſuch and ſuch of his Servants out unto<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> to Offer up his Son <hi>Iſaac</hi> and, to Try that Precious Faith of his own Elect, whereby like as <hi>Zebulun</hi> &amp; <hi>Naphtali were People that jeparded their lives unto the death.</hi> Judges. 5. 18. And hazarded their Lives for the Word of his Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, for his Truth and Righteouſneſs, as ſome of his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and Servants have done in former Generations. But Chriſtian People, Take this Counſel as from me, who have been ſomewhat Experienced in the wayes of God, whenſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ye perceive fears within you, as thoſe ſame fears do Relate to God, or your own Future State and Condition,) for from hence doth uſually ariſe all the fear, and all the Great Thought and Searching of Heart, whither this ſhall be indeed Happy or Miſerable) There learn to know the true cauſe of that fear, and then labour to Remove it. Now all fear doth uſually ariſe from Sin and Guilt, and therfore take away the Sin and Guilt, and the fear alſo will ceaſe. So that the Reſult of the whole is this, If thou Man or, Woman, wouldſt be indeed led in the way Everlaſting, thou muſt be ſure that there be no wicked way in thee. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 134.
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:152402:13"/> Thou muſt both Pray, <hi>Search me, O God, and know my heart<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> try me, and know my Thoughts.</hi> And thou muſt Endeavour the ſame thy ſelf, even to Search thy ſelf and know thy heart, to try thy ſelf and know thy thoughts, that there be no wicked way in thee, that thou liveſt in no known Sin, not reſerved Iniquity whatever, and thou leaveſt no Duty un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done. And that thou doſt not Omit, or ſlip any Opp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities of doing good. <hi>For to him that knoweth to do good, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> doeth it not, to him it is Sin,</hi> Jam. 4. 17. Finally Breth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Whatſoever Things are True, whatſoever Things are Ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, whatſoever Things are Juſt, whatſoever Things <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Pure, whatſoever Things are Lovely, whatſoever Thin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> are of Good Report, if there be any Vertue, and if there be any Praiſe, Think on theſe Things. O my Fellow Chriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians, Think often, Yea think alwayes on the Words of the <hi>Text</hi> I have Choſen this Day. If you do not Remember and carry away any thing of the Sermon, beſides <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſure to Remember, and carry away the Words of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> preſent <hi>Text,</hi> for that will be enough<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd ſufficient.</p>
            <p>If when any Good <hi>Thought</hi> or true <hi>Thoughts</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> in your Soul, when you like the <hi>Patriark Jacob,</hi> Vo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> unto him, <hi>the Lord ſhall be my God.</hi> Gen. 28. 21. And <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> thy Vows unto the moſt High.</hi> Pſal. 50. 14. When any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> his <hi>Truths</hi> comes into thy Mind, which either make the I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible God more known unto thee, or the things of h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Kingdom or concerning the World to come, even our Futu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> State and Condition therein; which ſame truth or truth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> do ſtir up or Quicken, Exhort and Actually Perſwade<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> do all the Words of his Law, to keep his Commandmen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> his <hi>Teſtimonies,</hi> and his <hi>Statutes,</hi> in all theſe and ſuch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Things,</hi> Be ſure to lift up thy heart towards God in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Words of my <hi>Text, O Lord God of Abraham, Iſaac, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Iſrael our F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>thers kept this for ever in the Imagination of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Thoughts of the Heart of thy People, and prepare their hea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> unto thee.</hi> I ſay again for thy more Remembrance and O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> ſervance thereof, in all theſe and ſuch like good caſes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Inſtances, <hi>Pray</hi> without ceaſing, and endeavour the ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> without ceaſing, <hi>O Lord God of Abraham, Iſaac, and of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> rael our Fathers, keep this for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ver in the Imagination of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Thoughts of the Hearts of thy People, and prepare their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> unto thee, Amen, So be it.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
